[SPEAKER_00]: One of the precepts is about training in regards to abstaining from intoxicants.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha did not list any specific items, and my impression is that some modern so-called drugs do not fall into the category of an intoxicant, such as LSD, ayahuasca, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have been used for a long time in ancient cultures as medicine, to open you up to a higher reality and become more receptive for spiritual values.
[SPEAKER_00]: In addition, they are used therapeutic, these days in ceremonies or as microdosing in psychotherapy.
[SPEAKER_00]: All this seems to indicate that they are no intoxicants, they rather heal than destroy.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I still have doubts if the criteria for intoxication that I apply are correct.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it only the results and side effects that something has, or is there a broader intoxication that underlies this?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the problem is the effect, for sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thing is, you have two sides to that coin.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is the...
[SPEAKER_01]: This is what that person called opening up to a higher reality, which is how it appears.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, there is the effect that it has on your mind, which is a more important thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the effect that it has is putting you out of touch with the ordinary reality, which is where your problems actually are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your problems were not in the higher reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: They were in this reality that you're trying to transcend.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't transcend it by replacing it with a different reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: You transcend it by understanding and overcoming the craving that you have in regard to the unpleasant things that manifest in this reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whatever you discover in a different reality cannot have any effect whatsoever on this reality and your mind's attitude towards this reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's kind of like saying, you will solve the problems that you experience at your workplace by going on vacation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, sure, you will stop experiencing the acute disturbances and people harassing you and stuff just because you went on vacation, but there is absolutely nothing being done about the root cause of the disturbance when you are at work.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the reason why you have to abstain from these intoxicants, not just because
[SPEAKER_01]: If it were just a temporary disconnection, just a temporary vacation, that would be fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, by taking intoxicants, you are training this habit that you already have, that everybody already has, of resolving their problems by going elsewhere, by changing the scenery, by going out of touch with them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just becoming oblivious about them.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a reason why that's appealing.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a reason why drugs are such a prevalent thing that people resort to.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because the mind wants that kind of escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: Escape through distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Escape through replacement.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it's just some people are willing to go very far with that attitude of distraction and replacement and oblivion to the point where they become alcoholics or drug addicts and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's completely irrelevant whether it gives you these side effects of, you know, health issues and and all that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is, in terms of the dhamma, is how it's training the attitude, again, that you already start with.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just making it worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of not facing suffering, not facing discomfort, understanding it and removing your craving in regard to it, it's training the the habit of just replacing the thing that causes you suffering with something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever higher reality you encounter, you might feel a relief because of that, because the
[SPEAKER_01]: The content that was triggering your craving changed, and it sort of fills you with this novelty.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in actuality, the same hindrances, the same craving, the same inclinations of the mind are still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just don't see them as an issue in this particular case, because of the novelty, because of the... the... yeah, temporary relief that it gives you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to stay there long enough, if that became your new reality, constantly,
[SPEAKER_01]: You would eventually realize, whatever higher reality I go to, the same problem remains, because it wasn't in the content of my perceptions, it's in how my mind craved.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, however far you go with that type of escape, which, by the way, is the same thing that people would try to get from their meditation, and it's just a completely misguided endeavor, whatever escape you go to, it has this
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just a replacement that relieves the tension just because it's different.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, replacing the content does nothing about why was the previous content an issue in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, it's a matter of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: However, whatever replacement you do, it's like, you know, when you've been living in the same house, in the same neighborhood, in the same country for decades, and then you get the option to go somewhere else, it's going to feel like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're going to feel excited and you're going to feel like, oh, I'm going to be able to escape all these issues finally, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, for the first few
[SPEAKER_01]: However long you live there, there's going to be a time, this honeymoon phase almost, where you still have a strong enough memory of those previous issues that this feels like it's not there anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problems have gone away.
[SPEAKER_01]: But eventually, because the mind is not trained, you will find yourself in the exact same position again.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why it's not a resolution at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's actually a deviation from the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's... when you go to the point of taking intoxicants, you're actually not just making a choice of replacing circumstances, which you will do to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's now a view, comes with a view, that this is a valid way to resolve your suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's just a very coarse example.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have also, for example, entertainment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Entertainment is the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like by watching a movie, by listening to music, by absorbing yourself in pleasant conversation with people you like and so on, it gives you this this change of scenery, where you don't have to deal with whatever issues were weighing on you, and it cultivates the exact same habit of
[SPEAKER_01]: Dealing with suffering by looking away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why that's also a more subtle form, but it's a restraint that is required for the same reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's to undo the habit of delusion, which is the third defilement.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, in fact, the Buddha said it's not just very hard to get rid of, but it's also very blameworthy, very problematic, because it's the root for the other two.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, sometimes people have this notion that, well, look, I'm not lustfully chasing after sensual objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not angry and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, yeah, watching movies or even intoxication with these spiritual drugs.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they don't realize that delusion is actually more harmful than the other two, because
[SPEAKER_01]: See, you wouldn't be resorting to sensuality, you wouldn't be resorting to ill-will as a means of resolving your suffering, unless you already had the view that changing the circumstances, that just replacing the content of what you experience, is a valid solution.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by feeding that view, you're feeding the potential for lust and aversion, even if it's not there right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're feeding the root that allows it to grow when those sense objects hit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind will be craving that replacement.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, you find yourself with this pleasure of seeing a sensual object, you want to replace that experience with going for the sensual object, getting more of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When something unpleasant strikes you, and that's factual, that's just how the experience comes up, but then you crave to replace it with a more pleasant experience that doesn't have that
[SPEAKER_01]: Unpleasant thing anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: It trains the same fundamental habit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Delusion trains the same fundamental habit that that is the basis for the other two types of defilement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could one say then that that's the... this principle of wanting to change the scenery, wanting to replace one experience with another,
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the criteria to judge whether things are an intoxicant or not?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people, obviously, they can come up with lists and items that they think that are intoxicants, which maybe even science might say they are intoxicants, but if you look at that principle, they might actually turn out not to be intoxicants.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And other things that are not seen as intoxicants are actually intoxicants.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, for instance, I think even things like coffee would be regarded as an intoxicant because it
[SPEAKER_01]: Changes your brain chemistry or and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, nobody would go for coffee as a means of forgetting about your problems.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's... it just doesn't have that effect.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't put you out of touch with the ordinary reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, yeah, alcohol, cannabis, spiritual drugs, LSD, mushrooms, DMT, all these things that people might think have a spiritual benefit, they do have that effect, and that's exactly why people would resort to them, out of wrong views, as a means to resolve
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't rely on a list, because God knows how many drugs there are, but what you have to rely on is
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, if you already see yourself inclining towards it because of this promise that it will help you forget about things, that it will give you something else that's better, a different kind of experience that's better than what you currently have, that's delusion already.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're trying to overcome what is actually still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like I said, it's not that your defilements are disappearing because you replace the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just covered up.
[SPEAKER_01]: They become less obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... if that's the appeal of it, then it's an intoxicant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or that's the effect of it, even if you're not thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Other people are pressuring into it, whatever it might be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you know that the effect will be that you'll be put into this different state where you don't have to deal as much with the pressures and sort of discomforts of ordinary reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's an intoxicant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, that means it doesn't necessarily need to be even a consumable substance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like I said before, meditation, in the way that's presented in most traditions today, is precisely that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a way to be out of touch with where the actual problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Resolving it temporarily, but then, you know, people expect that the solution will come by experiencing an even more special than the already special state that they have.
[SPEAKER_01]: They just keep chasing that after eventually it's special enough and that's going to resolve the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Failing to see that it's those very habits of the mind that manifest when they're not in... well, that become more obvious when they're not in those special states.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the fact that their mind can be upset by annoying situations.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that the mind can be entranced by pleasant things that arise when they're not in a hypnotic state.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they're doing absolutely nothing about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By replacing the content of their experience with these more special types that just cover up the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they would see as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, the thing is, they don't want to see it, but they would see that those habits of lust, those habits of longing, habits of expectation, of anticipation, of desire, are still underlying all those efforts to chase after a special experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that it doesn't count, because the content is different.
[SPEAKER_01]: But obviously, that's the wrong criteria, because the state of mind is not determined by what it is chasing after.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the attitude of chasing that's the issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what keeps you bound to saṃsāra and to suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I mean, someone could say in the in the context of caffeine, for example, like, you are tired, you are averse to the tiredness, and you want to replace that experience with the experience of being charged, being vital, feeling alive, obviously being functional as well, and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, there seems to be a, at least to some degree, a correlation that you are not happy with the present state and you take something.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, that principle can... applies almost to anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why anything could have a degree of unwholesomeness behind it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're taking caffeine because you can't deal with tiredness and you feel confined by it, then that right there is an opportunity for training.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, like, you wouldn't be resorting to that in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: As, like, it doesn't in and of itself put you out of touch with reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, eh... it doesn't make you... it's... let's say you have... you're dealing... dealing with, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know, issues in your interpersonal relationships, or, eh... pain, or... or sadness, or depression, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is not gonna put you and... and... and change the content of your thoughts and allow you to avoid all those memories and regrets or whatever you might have.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, it can... anything can serve.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you could say you eat.
[SPEAKER_01]: You eat food.
[SPEAKER_01]: The food helps you avoid the state of hunger.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's just the principle of action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, whenever you do anything, you're trying to replace the present state of affairs.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, there's a difference between replacing the present state of affairs and going out of touch with the
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's say the the the base where dukkha arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like so, eh... that base meaning sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, the six sense bases, which the Buddha said that's what you have to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where the problem arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go out of that or, well, you don't go out of it, but you you replace the content enough for you to not have to be
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to be concerned with it anymore, not to have to be concerned with understanding it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like a... you arrive at the solution to the completely wrong place.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to overcome the craving anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't experience the suffering, because the thing changed.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you have to avoid.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not think, oh, every action that I do is an issue because I'm replacing the present state of affairs.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, am I still going to be able or have a... have the need to understand the root of the problem, understand suffering, overcome craving in order to deal with the issue, in order to escape the issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, do I just escape circumstantially by changing the scenery, as I said?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, when I fail to change the scenery, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm done.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm back to where I started.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, with things that are not intoxicants, you will see it's going to leave you plenty of need to understand suffering in order to not experience it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, you might get rid of the tiredness, but something else will come up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like it's removing that opportunity.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not putting you completely out of touch with this space where these things can strike you, and then you're forced to be developed enough to not be affected by them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would be another way of thinking about it is, like, if you, let's say,
[SPEAKER_00]: On the subjects of old age, sickness, death, losing something that's dear to you, you would never resort to caffeine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: To forget about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would resolve certainly to alcohol, drugs, company, distractions, entertainment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that, yeah, might change the experience, but not, like you said, to the degree that you are actually forgetting about those issues.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, standing up, sitting down, going to sleep, brushing your teeth, taking medicine, all these things would change the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't, it doesn't put you out of the place where, like I said, things can strike you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And where it's obvious that you haven't developed yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not developing a habit of delusion, not by itself at least, and not as strongly, which is the habit of resolving the issue by changing the scenery.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, well, the habit of thinking that you can resolve the issue by changing the scenery.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking that you can overcome suffering by result... by changing the scenery.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it was clear to you that that's not possible, then it would be impossible for you to resort to intoxication, to resort to entertainment.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it wouldn't be impossible for you to drink caffeine, to stand up, to brush your teeth, to take medicine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not expecting that to be a result... eh... to be a resolution.